<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: 物理 | 桑弧蓬矢射四方]]></title>
  <link href="http://iphyer.github.com/blog/categories/物理/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://iphyer.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-08-24T11:59:19+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://iphyer.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[iphyer]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[iphyer@163.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[晶界内耗的读书报告]]></title>
    <link href="http://iphyer.github.com/blog/2015/01/11/lecture201501/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-11T16:17:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://iphyer.github.com/blog/2015/01/11/lecture201501</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="section">前言</h2>

<p>新的一年开始了，刚刚把年度工作报告写好了．还有两个星期，GRE最后的决战就要来了．上个星期去了琦叔GRE的400题和100题冲刺班可以说给自己吃了一次大补药，1.24再战GRE.</p>

<p>其实我想写写什么的，就是没有什么感觉，一种内疚和恶劣的情绪一直纠缠着自己，去死吧！真是太糟糕的感觉，干脆把2014年group meeting报告贴上来同时作为自己的最新博文吧.</p>

<p>今天看到的一条微博,在找到了原文<a href="http://news.qq.com/a/20150111/013503.htm">于敏院士：出国留学不要等到老了才落叶归根</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>于敏那时却不曾踏出国门一步，他对此有些许遗憾。“如果生在现在，重新上大学，我当然会留学。”他说，“土专家”不足为法，科学需要开放交流和广阔视野，但留学后须“回国再给国家做点事儿”，而且“不要到老了才回来，落叶归根只能起点肥料作用，应该开花结果的时候回来”。</p>
</blockquote>

<p>同时深切哀悼李小文院士，世间再无扫地僧，真本事真性情．</p>

<p>还是好好复习GRE吧！</p>

<h2 id="section-1">写好博客的作用</h2>

<p>今天发现自己在ChaseDream上发表的帖子被尚友论坛的版主转载了<a href="http://www.sharewithu.com/thread-738732-1-1.html">背单词的两个方法总结</a>，其实我发在尚友了，但是尚友不允许使用hide标签结果没有人顶贴帖子沉了，结果现在又让版主转载回来，真是Ｏ＿＿Ｏ＂…．</p>

<p>不过能够帮助到别人就是好的.</p>

<!--more-->

<h2 id="section-2">报告</h2>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-0.png" alt="tu0" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-1.png" alt="tu1" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-2.png" alt="tu2" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-3.png" alt="tu3" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-4.png" alt="tu4" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-5.png" alt="tu5" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-6.png" alt="tu6" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-7.png" alt="tu7" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-8.png" alt="tu8" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-9.png" alt="tu9" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-10.png" alt="tu10" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-11.png" alt="tu11" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-12.png" alt="tu12" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-13.png" alt="tu13" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-14.png" alt="tu14" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-15.png" alt="tu15" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-16.png" alt="tu16" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-17.png" alt="tu17" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-18.png" alt="tu18" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-19.png" alt="tu19" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-20.png" alt="tu20" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-21.png" alt="tu21" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-22.png" alt="tu22" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-23.png" alt="tu23" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-24.png" alt="tu24" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-25.png" alt="tu25" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-26.png" alt="tu26" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-27.png" alt="tu27" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-28.png" alt="tu28" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-29.png" alt="tu29" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-30.png" alt="tu30" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-31.png" alt="tu31" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-32.png" alt="tu32" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-33.png" alt="tu33" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-34.png" alt="tu34" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-35.png" alt="tu35" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-36.png" alt="tu36" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-37.png" alt="tu37" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-38.png" alt="tu38" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-39.png" alt="tu39" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/interficition/file-40.png" alt="tu40" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[关于玻璃转变物理模型的报告]]></title>
    <link href="http://iphyer.github.com/blog/2014/05/11/nc/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-11T21:57:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://iphyer.github.com/blog/2014/05/11/nc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="section">起因</h2>

<p>这是上课的时候做的一个关于玻璃转变的报告，这里贴上来，大家讨论讨论，我觉得以非晶为代表的人类向着无序结构求索的种种努力基本都是失败了的。</p>

<p>不知道大家怎么看？</p>

<!--more-->

<h2 id="section-1">报告</h2>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-0.png" alt="tu0" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-1.png" alt="tu1" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-2.png" alt="tu2" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-3.png" alt="tu3" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-4.png" alt="tu4" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-5.png" alt="tu5" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-6.png" alt="tu6" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-7.png" alt="tu7" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-8.png" alt="tu8" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-9.png" alt="tu9" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-10.png" alt="tu10" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-11.png" alt="tu11" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-12.png" alt="tu12" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-13.png" alt="tu13" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-14.png" alt="tu14" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-15.png" alt="tu15" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-16.png" alt="tu16" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-17.png" alt="tu17" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-18.png" alt="tu18" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-19.png" alt="tu19" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-20.png" alt="tu20" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-21.png" alt="tu21" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-22.png" alt="tu22" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-23.png" alt="tu23" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-24.png" alt="tu24" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-25.png" alt="tu25" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-26.png" alt="tu26" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-27.png" alt="tu27" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-28.png" alt="tu28" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-29.png" alt="tu29" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/NC/file-30.png" alt="tu30" /></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ising相变的模拟]]></title>
    <link href="http://iphyer.github.com/blog/2014/05/11/ising/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-11T20:13:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://iphyer.github.com/blog/2014/05/11/ising</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="section">起因</h2>

<p>这是上学期的一个Project，似乎不应该现在才放出来。但是老师一直没有给分，因为是论文的一部分，全文发上来万一来个查重什么。所以等到老师终于给分了，就直接贴上来了。</p>

<p>这是一份英文的报告。</p>

<p>Latex转过来的时候的参考文献格式我就没怎么换，都放在最后了。</p>

<!--more-->

<h2 id="abstract">abstract</h2>

<p>In this lab experiment, we use importance sampling Monte Carlo techniques to study $60 \times 60 $ 2-D Ising Model. We will further discuss the thermal properties of Ising Model.</p>

<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>

<p>Ising Model is one of the most important the theoretical model in statistical physics,which is proposed first to explain the start of ferro-magnetism. The central thought of Ising Model is representing real system like magnetic Curie points or order-disorder phenomena transitions in alloy as  molecules interacting with nearest neighbour in a lattice \cite{Rev}. Although Ising Model was scorned and ignored by most scientists during its early ages \cite{Rev}, it has gained more and more popularity in the science community for both its multi-disciplines application in physics, chemistry, metallurgy,and mathematics and its simple and elegant lattice models physical intuition.</p>

<p>Ising Model can be simply described as the lattice model with $-1$ or $+1$ spins constrained to the site of lattice and spin interactions only exist between nearest neighbours.</p>

<p>1-D Ising Model is proposed and solved by Krnst Ising and his PhD supervisor Wilhelm Lenz and their result shows there is no phase transition \cite{Rev}. However, it is until 1944, Onsager obtained exact results of 2-D Ising Mode and the analysis shows that there is a second order phase transition \cite{guide}. But 3-D Ising Model is still no exact solution.</p>

<p>In this report, we will generally focus on 2-D Ising Model and the lattice size is $60 \times 60$ and the temperature will be decreased from 3.5 to 1.5 by step 0.1 ,then increased form 1.5 to 3.5</p>

<h2 id="algorithm">Algorithm</h2>

<p>Generally we simulate Ising Model following the rule of importance sampling which only counts those configurations that contribute greater to the final state of system.</p>

<p>To realize this, we use Metropolis Method. In the classic, Metropolis Method generates configuration form the previous state using the energy difference dependent transition probability which means that the new state can be produced by old state multiplies the transition probability. This procedure can be described by a master equation:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
\frac{\partial P_n(t)}{\partial t}=-\sum_{n \neq m}[P_n(t)W_{n \rightarrow n } - P_m(t)W_{m \to n} ]
</script>

<p>where $P_n(t)$ is the probability of the system being in state n at time, and $W_{n \to m }$ is the transition rate for $ n \to m$.</p>

<p>In equilibrium, we get $\frac{\partial P_n(t)}{\partial t} =0 $ and this means that the right two terms of equation \eqref{masterequ} is equal which gives </p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
P_n(t)W_{n \rightarrow n }=P_m(t)W_{m \to n} 
</script>

<p>And based on the knowledge of Statistical Physics we can know that the probability of n state occurring in a classical system is given by:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
P_n(t)=e^{-E_n/k_BT}/Z
</script>

<p>where Z is the partition function.</p>

<p>However, we actually know little of the system’s partition function. To avoid this difficulty, we generate each new state directly from the preceding state and repeating this we get a Markov Chain of states. So if we produce the n state form m state, the relative transition probability will only depends on the energy difference between the two states which is :</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
\Delta E= E_n - E_m
</script>

<p>So the uncertain partition function cancels.</p>

<p>Any transition rate satisfying detailed balance is acceptable in Monte Carlo Simulation. And in this case, we use Metropolis Scheme is </p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">% &lt;![CDATA[

W_{n \to m} =
\left\{
  \begin{matrix}
    \tau_0^{-1} \exp(-\Delta E/ k_BT), &  \Delta E > 0\\ 
     \tau_0^{-1}, & \Delta E<0 
  \end{matrix}
\right.
 %]]&gt;</script>

<p>where $\tau_0$ is the time required to attempt one move form old state to new state which is a spin-flip action in Ising Model.</p>

<p>So we can describe Metropolis Importance Sampling Motel Carlo Scheme as following :</p>

<ul>
  <li>Choose an initial state</li>
  <li>Choose a site i</li>
  <li>Calculate the energy change $\Delta E$ which results from if the spin at site i is overturned </li>
  <li>Generate a random number r that  $0&lt;r&lt;1$</li>
  <li>Go the next site and go to step 3</li>
  <li>After enough steps, sample needed physical prosperities </li>
</ul>

<p>In the simulation, we use the reduced unit to simply the calculation and shorten the time of computing. </p>

<p>Generally, we make that the unit of energy is $J$, the unit of length is 1 and unit of mass is also 1. In this unit system, temperature is $J/k_B$,where $k_B$ is the Boltzmann constant. If we want to further simply the unit system, we can set $J=1$, so that the temperature is in unit of $1/k_B$.</p>

<h2 id="calculating-observables">Calculating Observables</h2>

<p>After we have set up the scheme for the The Metropolis Algorithm, we further discuss the observables or those physics quantities we are interested in.</p>

<p>We know that the expectation value of an observable A can be written as:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
\left \langle A \right \rangle=\frac{\sum_r A_re^{-\beta E_r}}{\sum_r e^{\beta E_r}} 
</script>

<p>where $A_r$ is the value of A for the state r and $E_r$ is the energy for the state r.</p>

<p>And using The Metropolis Algorithm, we can get many interesting prosperities about the system. </p>

<p>For system energy $E$ we have </p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
E=-J \sum_{i,j} S_i S_j
</script>

<p>where $J$ is the interaction  constant between the neighbour spins.</p>

<p>For magnetization, we have </p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
M=  \sum_{i}^{N} S_i 
</script>

<p>where $N$ is the total number of the spins.</p>

<p>For specific heat, we have:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
C_v=\frac{\partial E}{\partial T}=-\frac{\beta}{T}\left[\left \langle E^2 \right \rangle -\left( \left \langle E \right \rangle \right)^2 \right]
</script>

<p>Incidentally, this is known as the Fluctuation Dissipation Theorem.</p>

<p>Also for magnetic susceptibility, $\chi $, can be written in terms of the variance in the magnetization:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
\chi=\frac{\partial  \left \langle M \right \rangle}{\partial H}=\beta\left[\left \langle M^2 \right \rangle -\left( \left \langle M \right \rangle \right)^2 \right]
</script>

<p>So we need to keep record of $E, E^2 , M , $ and $M^2$ , we can get the evolution of the energy, the magnetization, the specific heat, and the magnetic susceptibility.</p>

<h2 id="algorithm-details">Algorithm Details</h2>
<p>During the program of Monte Carlo Simulation, there are generally two details needed to pay attention to. The first one is how to calculate energy difference between the old state and new one.The second one is how to realize periodic boundary conditions.</p>

<h3 id="calculating-energy-difference">Calculating Energy Difference</h3>
<p>If we just use the common method to calculate the energy changes, the amount of calculations will be huge but if we further explore the different cases in energy changes there are only 5 results will happen if we change the spin of one site.</p>

<p><img src="/images/Ising/5case.png" alt="tu1" /></p>

<p>Now if we assume that we have get one site $(i,j)$ to change its spin, first we make it has spin $-1$. So if it were overturned, the spin is $+1$.Now considering its nearest four neighbours it will be only 5 cases if you take symmetry into consideration. The 5 cases are like figure \ref{5case} has shown.</p>

<p>So we can get a table of energy changes as table \ref{energychangeminus}, here we use the symbol $+$ and $-$ to represent up and down spin. Following the same routine, we can get the energy changes of up spin as table \ref{energychangeup}</p>

<p><img src="/images/Ising/table.png" alt="tu1" /></p>

<p>Based on table \ref{energychangeminus} and table \ref{energychangeup}, we can conclude that the energy change of turning site $(i,j)$ is equation \eqref{engchange}:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
\Delta E = 2S_i \sum_{n.n(j)}S_j
</script>

<p>where $n.n$ means the nearest four neighbours of site $(i,j)$.</p>

<h3 id="periodic-boundary-conditions">Periodic Boundary Conditions</h3>

<p>Because our simulations are performed on infinite systems, so we must take the effect of those edges and surfaces into consideration because they may be different from those in the body or inner part of the system. We can effectively eliminated these boundaries by wrapping the $N \times N$ Ising  lattice on a the $ (N+1) \times (N+1)$ one.</p>

<p>The common periodic boundary conditions may be like this:</p>

<p><img src="/images/Ising/mod.png" alt="tu1" /></p>

<p>where $ip1,im1,jp1,jm1$ means plus and minus 1 form i and j and $\mod$ means modular arithmetic and L is the size of the lattice.</p>

<p>But this involves too many computations for $mod$ can not be computed easily. But we can referred to two tables to simply the calculation for periodic boundary condition only happens on the edges of lattice, which means that the index of one spin site $(i,j)$ must have this relations:$i=1 , i= L$ or $j= 1 , j= L$.So we can calculated those periodic boundary conditions before which can also fasten the simulation. </p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>After doing all the simulation work, we will further discuss the propensities of Ising Model.</p>

<h3 id="observables-calculation">Observables Calculation</h3>
<p>As figure \ref{energy} has shown, energy is a continuous function of temperature, which, as we
expect, increases as a function of T .</p>

<p><img src="/images/Ising/energy.jpeg" alt="tu1" /></p>

<p>As figure \ref{mag} has shown, magnetization drops off sharply near the critical temperature,
which, in our units where k = J = 1, is approximately 2.3.</p>

<p><img src="/images/Ising/mag.jpeg" alt="tu1" /></p>

<p>As figure \ref{sheat} has shown, specific heat has a peak at the critical temperature.</p>

<p><img src="/images/Ising/specificheat.jpeg" alt="tu1" /></p>

<p>As figure \ref{magv} has shown,magnetic susceptibility has a sharp jump at the critical temperature.</p>

<p><img src="/images/Ising/magv.jpeg" alt="tu1" /></p>

<h3 id="average-accepting-rate">Average Accepting Rate</h3>
<p>And in figure \ref{acrate} we show the change of accepting rate. We can easily find out that the accepting rate increases when temperature does. This is just what we except. When temperature increases, a single site overturn will be less important to the change of system energy or we can say when temperature increases, the spins will be more disordered than they are at low temperature. At low temperature, all the spins are like frozen at their own site and less likely to change their direction.    </p>

<p><img src="/images/Ising/acceptingrate.jpeg" alt="tu1" /></p>

<h3 id="phase-transition">Phase Transition</h3>

<p><img src="/images/Ising/transfernew.png" alt="tu2" /></p>

<p>Then in figure \ref{transfer} we show the phase transition in Ising Model. In figure \ref{transfer} from top to bottom, temperature goes from 3.5 to 1.5.</p>

<p>Following we will show three key the configuration of three states at temperature 3.5, 2.5 ,1.5 in figure \ref{configure}</p>

<p><img src="/images/Ising/1.png" alt="tu2" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/Ising/2.png" alt="tu2" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/Ising/3.png" alt="tu2" /></p>

<h3 id="equilibrium-time">Equilibrium Time</h3>

<p>In my simulation, I set  $40 \% $ of the total Monte Carol Move to be the equilibrium stage. And this seems works fine when I set $mc_ total_steps=50000000$ which means the program will try to overturn the spin of Isng Model Lattice 50000000 times.</p>

<p>But if the $mc_ total_steps$ is less the result’s accuracy will suffer.For example figure \ref{mag500000} is the magnetization change of $mc_ total_steps=500000$.</p>

<p><img src="/images/Ising/magnetization.jpeg" alt="tu2" /></p>

<p>If you compare figure \ref{mag500000} with figure \ref{mag} you will find that figure \ref{mag} is much better. And nonetheless to say, specific heat, the image is wrong if  mc_ total_steps is low which also means not enough equilibrium time.</p>

<h3 id="correlation">Correlation</h3>
<p>Generally speaking, there are two kinds of correlations existing in Ising Model: one is time correlation, the other is space correlation. Below we will focus on both two kinds.</p>

<h4 id="time--correlation">Time  Correlation</h4>

<p>As we use Monte Carlo Step Time as the unit of our simulation time unit, so time correlation can be also explained as the Monte Carlo Move Step Correlation.So different numbers of simulation steps can result different result which has been explained in previous section \ref{equ} Equilibrium Time.</p>

<h4 id="space-correlation">Space Correlation</h4>

<p>Because a change of one spin site may result another change of another spin site, we can define a correlation length to represent this effect, which is also known as space correlation. So if the distance of two spin sites is within correlation length we think they are coupled or interacted and if not, we ignore their correlation. </p>

<p>In theory, we can define correlation between two spin sites as:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
 Cor =  \left \langle (S_i - \left \langle S_i \right \rangle )( S_j - \left \langle S_j \right \rangle ) \right \rangle = \left \langle S_i S_j \right \rangle - \left \langle S_i \right \rangle  \left \langle S_j \right \rangle 
</script>

<p>And one can easily guess correlation between two spin sites must be related with the distance of two spin sites and may also be related with temperature.To be simple, I choose spin site$(30,30)$ and its neighbours $(31,31),(34,34),(37,37),(40,40),(43,43)$ to calculate their correlation and show their relation ship of distance and temperature.</p>

<p>The result is figure \ref{corr} has shown.</p>

<p><img src="/images/Ising/corr.jpeg" alt="tu2" /></p>

<p>We can see that when the temperature is high, the correlation is weak but when temperature approximates the critical temperature where phase transition happens the correlation jumps up quickly. So we can say that phase transition is closely related with correlation between different spins. Also figure \ref{corr} tells us that at a specific temperature the nearer the stronger correlation . If we want to define some  correlation length of spin sites, it seems that we can set the correlation length between $2 \sim 3$ at high temperature. And at low temperature,correlation length is less obvious for the very strong correlation interaction.</p>

<h3 id="initial-conformation-dependence">Initial Conformation dependence</h3>

<p>Based on my study, I think initial conformation is useless for the final result of Ising Model if you set a large enough total number of simulation steps. But I do agree, that initial conformation can influence the equilibrium time and large enough total number of simulation steps can cancel its effect.</p>

<h2 id="programme-code">Programme Code</h2>

<pre><code>!**********************************************************************
!The programe performs Motel Carlo Simulation for 2D Ising Model.
!**********************************************************************
program main

implicit none

! Parameter declarations:
integer,parameter :: nrow=60
integer,parameter :: ncol=60
integer,parameter :: mc_total_steps=50000000
integer,parameter :: mc_eq_steps=20000000
integer,parameter :: mc_sample_steps=50000
real,parameter    :: maxtemperature=3.5         
real,parameter     :: mintemperature=1.5
real,parameter     :: deltatemperature=0.1

! Variable declarations:
integer             :: A(nrow,ncol)   
integer             :: ip(60),im(60),jp(60),jm(60)
integer             :: i
integer             :: j
integer             :: mc_counting
integer             :: mc_success_move
integer             :: samplenum

real                :: RanNum
real                :: Tnow

character(len=70) :: filename
character(len=70) :: captionname

!Sample Variable declarations:
real                :: energysum
real                :: energy2sum
real                :: mangentsum
real                :: mangent2sum
real                :: energysumtemp
real                :: energy2sumtemp
real                :: mangentsumtemp
real                :: mangent2sumtemp





!-----------------Initialization--------------------------------------------------!
do i =1,nrow
    do j=1,ncol
        call random_number(RanNum)
        if(RanNum &gt;= 0.5) then
            A(i,j)=1
        else
            A(i,j)=-1
        end if


    end do
end do

call plot_file ( nrow, ncol, A, 'Initial Configuration', 'ising_2d_initial.txt', &amp;
    'ising_2d_initial.png' )
!calculate the call peridoic boundary condition(ip,im,jp,jm)
call peridoicboundary(ip,im,jp,jm)

!-----------------MCSimulation and Sampleing------------------------!
	 Tnow=maxtemperature
	 
 do  while(Tnow&gt;=mintemperature)
	 mc_counting=0
	 mc_success_move=0
	 energysum=0
	 energy2sum=0
 	 mangentsum=0
	 mangent2sum=0
	 samplenum=0

	  
	 write(*,*) Tnow

	do while(mc_counting&lt;= mc_total_steps)
		call mc_onestep_move(A,ip,im,jp,jm,Tnow,mc_success_move)
		mc_counting=mc_counting+1
		if((mc_counting &gt; mc_eq_steps) .and. (MOD(mc_counting,mc_sample_steps)==0))	then
			mangentsumtemp=0
			energysumtemp=0
			energy2sumtemp=0
			mangent2sumtemp=0
			
			do i =1,nrow
				do j=1,ncol
				mangentsumtemp=mangentsumtemp+A(i,j)
				energysumtemp=energysumtemp+(A(ip(i),j)+A(im(i),j)+A(i,jp(j))+A(i,jm(j)))*A(i,j)*(-0.5)
				end do
			end do
			mangentsum=mangentsum+abs(mangentsumtemp/3600.0)
			energysum=energysum+energysumtemp/3600.0
			 
			
            energy2sumtemp=(energysumtemp/3600.0)**2
			mangent2sumtemp=(abs(mangentsumtemp/3600.0))**2
			energy2sum=energy2sum+energy2sumtemp
			mangent2sum=mangent2sum+mangent2sumtemp
			 

			samplenum=samplenum+1
			 
		else 			  
		end if
     
	end do	
!------------------------saving result-------------------------------------------!
 
	  
  if (Tnow&lt;=1.0) then  
  write (filename, '("plotdata0", F2.1)' )  Tnow
  else
  write (filename, '("plotdata", F3.1)' ) Tnow
  end if
  open (file='resulrsummary.txt',unit=16,position='append')
  write (16,*) &amp; 
  Tnow,mc_success_move,mangentsum/samplenum,mangent2sum/samplenum,energysum/samplenum,energy2sum/samplenum
  close (16)
  if (Tnow&lt;=1.0) then  
  write (captionname, '("Temperature=0", F2.1)' )  Tnow
  else
  write (captionname, '("Temperature=", F3.1)' ) Tnow
  end if
  call plot_file ( nrow, ncol, A, trim(captionname)//'Configuration', trim(filename)//'.txt', &amp;
     trim(filename)//'.png' )
   
!-----------------Next temperature------------------------!

Tnow=Tnow-deltatemperature	
end do

write(*,*) 'Done!'
end program



subroutine peridoicboundary(ip,im,jp,jm)
!*****************************************************************************80
!this subroutine caculate the peridoic boundary conditions for simulation
!
integer :: i
integer :: ip(60),im(60),jp(60),jm(60)

do i=1,60
	ip(i)=i+1
	im(i)=i-1
	jp(i)=i+1
	jm(i)=i-1
end do
ip(60)=1
im(1)=60
jp(60)=1
jm(1)=60
end


subroutine mc_onestep_move(M,xp,xm,yp,ym,T,mc_success_move)
!*****************************************************************************80
!this subroutine perform one move of Monte Carlo setp which also means turn one
!site of Ising Model up or down against the previous state. Then we caculate the 
!energy difference to determine whether this move is accepted or not.
! 
implicit none
real    :: x
real    :: y
real    :: energy_difference
real    :: neighbour_spin_sum
real    :: pro
real    :: T
real    :: judgement
integer :: mc_success_move
integer :: M(60,60) 
integer :: xp(60),xm(60),yp(60),ym(60)
integer :: xint
integer :: yint
call random_number(x)
call random_number(y)
xint=int(60*x)
yint=int(60*y)
if(xint==0) then
xint=1
else 
end if
if(yint==0) then
yint=1
else
end if

neighbour_spin_sum=M(xp(xint),yint)+M(xm(xint),yint)+M(xint,yp(yint))+M(xint,ym(yint))
energy_difference=(2)*M(xint,yint)*neighbour_spin_sum
pro=exp((-1)*energy_difference/T)

call random_number(judgement)
If (judgement&lt;pro) then
	M(xint,yint)=(-1)*M(xint,yint)
	mc_success_move=mc_success_move+1
else
	continue
end if
end



subroutine plot_file ( m, n, c1, title, plot_filename, png_filename )

!*****************************************************************************80
!
!! PLOT_FILE writes the current configuration to a GNUPLOT plot file.
!
!  Licensing:
!
!    This code is distributed under the GNU LGPL license.
!
!  Modified:
!
!    29 June 2013
!
!  Author:
!
!    John Burkardt
!
!  Parameters:
!
!    Input, integer ( kind = 4 ) M, N, the number of rows and columns.
!
!    Input, integer ( kind = 4 ) C1(M,N), the current state of the system.
!
!    Input, character ( len = * ) TITLE, a title for the plot.
!
!    Input, character ( len = * ) PLOT_FILENAME, a name for the GNUPLOT
!    command file to be created.
!
!    Input, character ( len = * ) PNG_FILENAME, the name of the PNG graphics
!    file to be created.
!
  implicit none

  integer ( kind = 4 ) m
  integer ( kind = 4 ) n

  integer ( kind = 4 ) c1(m,n)
  integer ( kind = 4 ) i
  integer ( kind = 4 ) j
  character ( len = * ) plot_filename
  integer ( kind = 4 ) plot_unit
  character ( len = * ) png_filename
  real ( kind = 8 ) ratio
  character ( len = * ) title
  integer ( kind = 4 ) x1
  integer ( kind = 4 ) x2
  integer ( kind = 4 ) y1
  integer ( kind = 4 ) y2

  call get_unit ( plot_unit )

  open ( unit = plot_unit, file = plot_filename, status = 'replace' )

  ratio = real ( n, kind = 8 ) / real ( m, kind = 8 )

  write ( plot_unit, '(a)' ) 'set term png'
  write ( plot_unit, '(a)' ) 'set output "' // trim ( png_filename ) // '"'
  write ( plot_unit, '(a,i4,a)' ) 'set xrange [ 0 : ', m, ' ]'
  write ( plot_unit, '(a,i4,a)' ) 'set yrange [ 0 : ', n, ' ]'
  write ( plot_unit, '(a)' ) 'set nokey'
  write ( plot_unit, '(a)' ) 'set title "' // trim ( title ) // '"'
  write ( plot_unit, '(a)' ) 'unset tics'

  write ( plot_unit, '(a,g14.6)' ) 'set size ratio ', ratio
  do j = 1, n
    y1 = j - 1
    y2 = j
    do i = 1, m
      x1 = m - i
      x2 = m + 1 - i
      if ( c1(i,j) &lt; 0 ) then
        write ( plot_unit, '(a,i3,a,i3,a,i3,a,i3,a)' ) 'set object rectangle from ', &amp;
          x1, ',', y1, ' to ', x2, ',', y2, ' fc rgb "blue"'
      else
        write ( plot_unit, '(a,i3,a,i3,a,i3,a,i3,a)' ) 'set object rectangle from ', &amp;
          x1, ',', y1, ' to ', x2, ',', y2, ' fc rgb "red"'
      end if
    end do
  end do

  write ( plot_unit, '(a)' ) 'plot 1'
  write ( plot_unit, '(a)' ) 'quit'

  close ( unit = plot_unit )

  write ( *, '(a)' ) ' '
  write ( *, '(a)' ) '  Created the gnuplot graphics file "' // trim ( plot_filename ) // '".'

  return
end

subroutine get_unit ( iunit )

!*****************************************************************************80
!
!! GET_UNIT returns a free FORTRAN unit number.
!
!  Discussion:
!
!    A "free" FORTRAN unit number is a value between 1 and 99 which
!    is not currently associated with an I/O device.  A free FORTRAN unit
!    number is needed in order to open a file with the OPEN command.
!
!    If IUNIT = 0, then no free FORTRAN unit could be found, although
!    all 99 units were checked (except for units 5, 6 and 9, which
!    are commonly reserved for console I/O).
!
!    Otherwise, IUNIT is a value between 1 and 99, representing a
!    free FORTRAN unit.  Note that GET_UNIT assumes that units 5 and 6
!    are special, and will never return those values.
!
!  Licensing:
!
!    This code is distributed under the GNU LGPL license.
!
!  Modified:
!
!    26 October 2008
!
!  Author:
!
!    John Burkardt
!
!  Parameters:
!
!    Output, integer ( kind = 4 ) IUNIT, the free unit number.
!
  implicit none

  integer ( kind = 4 ) i
  integer ( kind = 4 ) ios
  integer ( kind = 4 ) iunit
  logical lopen

  iunit = 0

  do i = 1, 99

    if ( i /= 5 .and. i /= 6 .and. i /= 9 ) then

      inquire ( unit = i, opened = lopen, iostat = ios )

      if ( ios == 0 ) then
        if ( .not. lopen ) then
          iunit = i
          return
        end if
      end if

    end if

  end do

  return
end
</code></pre>

<h2 id="reference">Reference</h2>

<p>\bibitem{Rev} Brush S G. History of the Lenz-Ising model[J]. Reviews of Modern Physics, 1967, 39(4): 883.</p>

<p>\bibitem{guide} Landau D P, Binder K. A guide to Monte Carlo simulations in statistical physics[M]. Cambridge university press, 2009,P68.</p>

<p>\bibitem{john} John Burkardt,Monte Carlo 2D Ising Model Fortran90 Code,\url{http://people.sc.fsu.edu/~jburkardt/f_src/ising<em>2d_simulation/ising</em>2d_simulation.html}</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[X ray峰的指标化]]></title>
    <link href="http://iphyer.github.com/blog/2013/12/09/x-rayfeng-de-zhi-biao-hua/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-09T14:50:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://iphyer.github.com/blog/2013/12/09/x-rayfeng-de-zhi-biao-hua</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="section">前言</h2>

<p>X射线课的一篇作业，有点意思，所以贴出来。</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>EuTiO3具有理想的立方钙钛矿结构,其晶格常数与SrTiO3的
相等,均为3.905 Å,这二者可以组成一个比较理想无应力
体系,用于研究复杂结构的氧化物薄膜无应力生长的机
理。
从课程网站上下载实验数据,使用任一你喜欢的软件画出$EuTiO_3$粉末的XRD谱,然后计算并标出各个衍射峰的指数(写出计算过程和结果)。</p>
</blockquote>

<p>具体的数据在这里(http://pan.baidu.com/s/1w3kOc)</p>

<!--more-->

<p>首先先做图，看一看这个X射线的峰分布。结果如下，这里是以$2 \theta$为横坐标画图：</p>

<p><img src="/images/Xray/XRD.png" alt="tu1" /></p>

<p>由Bragg公式：</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
2 d_{hkl} \sin \theta = \lambda
</script>

<p>然后考虑到EuTiO_3是立方晶系，我们有 </p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">d_{hkl}=\frac{a}{\sqrt{h^2+k^2+l^2}}</script>

<p>，这里a为晶格常数。</p>

<p>所以简单的变形就有：</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
\frac{\lambda}{2d_{hkl}}=\sin \theta
</script>

<p>知道了峰的位置($2\theta$)也就可以求出$\sin \theta$,同时一般X射线的波长也是已知的，这里是可以直接从X射线的数据文件中读出来为$1.540562$ Å。</p>

<p>然后是计算相对应的晶面指数的对应的X射线的$\frac{\lambda}{2d_{hkl}}$，具体可以用python来解决。</p>

<p>```python</p>

<h1 id="coding-utf-8---">-<em>- coding: utf-8 -</em>-</h1>
<p>”””
Created on Thu Dec  5 00:26:21 2013</p>

<p>@author: famer
“””</p>

<p>import math as m</p>

<p>for h in range(0,5):
    for k in range(0,5):
        for l in range(0,5):
        	print h,k,l,(1.540562/3.905)*m.sqrt(h<strong>2+k</strong>2+l**2)/2.0</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>其实就是生成一系列的随着晶面指数变化的$\frac{\lambda}{2d_{hkl}}$。这里需要注意Python的sin是有范围限制的且以弧度为单位。</p>

<p>当然生成的数据有的时候会有重复，这个时候需要排序数据，然后挑选出合适的数据。最后结果如下：</p>

<p><img src="/images/Xray/Graph4.png" alt="tu1" /></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[物理思考]]></title>
    <link href="http://iphyer.github.com/blog/2013/12/09/wu-li-si-kao/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-09T14:46:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://iphyer.github.com/blog/2013/12/09/wu-li-si-kao</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="section">前言</h2>
<p>====
这是一篇哲学课的作业，分为两个部分，请大家指正。</p>

<h2 id="section-1">关于科研意义的一些思考</h2>
<p>======================</p>

<p>谈到科研的意义其实我们就要探讨科研是什么。单单就这个而言其实也是非常复杂的，我相信有很多的专家做出过他们自己的判断，这里我从自己的角度来解读科研的含义。而受限制于自己所学物理专业的因素，我可能更多的从自然科学学科的角度来谈自己的看法。正因为如此，我的看法可能较浓的物理学科色彩，必定有偏颇之处，请老师指正。</p>

<!--more-->

<h3 id="section-2">科研的定义</h3>
<hr />

<p>最基本的科研有广义和狭义的区别。</p>

<p>广义上，人们的一切对于未知事物的探索都可以称之为科研。比如很多小朋友小时候喜欢拆卸收音机等小玩意或者抓起小虫子习惯性地玩上一会都可以算是科研。前者可以参看美国物理大师费曼的自传《“别闹了，费曼先生”》里面他亲口讲述了自己小时候是怎么从修理收音机里探索电磁波的秘密的；后者的话法国昆虫学家法布尔的传世名著《昆虫记》就是明证。如果我们从事物在不断发展而且这些发展是前后联系的角度看，没有任何借口，我们否认这些是科研。从广义科学的角度看，什么是科学——为了满足人类的好奇心而作出的思维分析或者动手实验都是科学。比如爱因斯坦的Follow
Your Curiosity（“我没什么特殊的才能，我只是保持了我持续不断的好奇心。”）。</p>

<p>狭义上的科研，当然就是人们通常意义上通常上指称的科研，也就是通常在电视上可以看到那些在实验室埋头苦干、艰苦奋斗的科学家们。这一类科研最大特点往往是专业化，很多的时候科学家才是绝对的精英主义者，在某个领域内只有专业精英才是大家公认的。你需要使用专门的表述语言，专门的研究设备，专门的实验方法，专门的设计思路实现专门的科研目标。比如很多顶尖的的理论物理文章其实不单单对外行高深莫测，对于内行人也是头疼不已，仅仅是顺着文章读读都是佶屈聱牙的。很多理论物理专业的同学往往一周只能读一篇论文，对于特别重要的论文，开组会的时候会一个导师带着几个同学每次$2 \sim 3$页的慢慢读下去，一段段的读，遇到不懂的时候互相讨论，再演算结果。因为很多时候前后差一个符号就会导致结果相差千里。比如下面这个故事其实就是理论物理广为流传的一个小故事，我们从这个故事可以窥理论物理一斑:</p>

<p><code>Schwinger以超强的算功闻名。有段时间 Schwinger在Oppenenheimer(奥本海默）那里干活。有两个年轻的物理学家来找奥本海默请教一个问题。此时奥本海默已经进入脱产的老板阶段，就告诉他们这样这样算，回去自己算吧。当天Schwinger狂算了一个晚上，最后就把结果写在一破纸上，塞到一口袋里。过了5、6个月，那两个人回来了，高兴把结果拿给老板看，Oppenenheimer就对Schwinger说你不是早就搞定了吗，你去对一下。Schwinger就回去把所有的衣服翻了遍，终于找到了那个小纸团。对了一下，回来告诉大部分是对的，只差了一个因子。于是 Oppenenheimer转身就对那两个家伙说：“你们赶快回去，找找看哪里少了个因子。”结果还真是这个结果。</code></p>

<p>当然你只要google下这个故事就会发现只有个叫Beautiful Creatures：Selected
Physical
Gossip<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>的网站有记录这个故事，其他很多是国人转载来转载去的二手货，这里我其实也不想考察故事的真伪，关键是这个故事表达出专业主义统治下，狭义科学的精英主义的来源和原因。因为高度专门化后的现实说明，精英与一般科研工作者存在巨大差异。</p>

<p>在很长的历史时期内这两者是不矛盾的，很多的时候甚至是重合的。比如人类认识到使用火来烹饪食物，发现柳树皮可以治疗感冒，甚至《红楼梦》中提到的贾府养伤的秘方——“且饿他几日”等等都可以算是广义上的科学探索，但是同时也可以算是狭义上的一次不太规范但弥足珍贵的实验探索。比如可以治疗感冒的柳树皮其实是很多老中医的一剂重要灵药。从某种意义上，中医在很早的历史阶段就出现了现代狭义科学的实践传统。</p>

<p>但是到了以电气为代表的第二次工业革命以后，两者出现了越来越多的分离。第一次工业革命，无论是珍妮织布机、火车、还是蒸汽机都是工程师在生产第一线的发明，可以说他们直接灵感来源就是实践生产。在这个阶段生产的大发展对于科学往往还是起到促进作用。但是到了第二次工业革命，从奥斯陆发现电磁感应，第一次联系电磁现象到法拉第发现磁生电直到麦克斯韦的电磁学方程组乃至于赫兹的实验验证，科学终于发挥出指导性作用，很多的电磁应用是人们在理论上构建并且预测出可行用途随后才投入研发并发明出来的。最著名的例子就是无线电通信，当然它的发现人赫兹本身对于利用电磁波通信持否定态度，这才促成马可尼被誉为无线电通信第一人。</p>

<p>随后，随着质能方程的提出，人类第一次预测了一种可以毁灭地球的武器并且最终实现。当然从严谨的角度，质能方程对于原子弹的关系就和风筝对于航天飞机一样。但是另一个更加明确的例子可能就是量子力学和现代计算机，当我在电脑前打下这篇论文的时候，第一个感谢的人或许该是普郎克，量子力学之父。正是量子力学从理论上指导了晶体管的设计，无论是双极性晶体管（BJT）还是场效应晶体管（FET），不使用量子力学是没法彻底理解的，更谈不上设计出可靠的器件。</p>

<p>基于科学的巨大作用，人们转而支持科学的研究，越来越多的人从事科学研究后带来了更多的科学发现，更多的科学发现直接推动了科学的进步。科学的进步也就带来专业主义的盛行。专业主义往往是目标指向性的，需要专门资金的支持和专门专业的从业人员。正如很多课题组经常做的，往往一个科研课题的开题是从构思出一个可以申请到经费的科研课题开始的。从某种意义上，狭义科研既有专业主义优势，比如高效，重点突出；又具有目标指向的新的特点，比如压力，领域专门化。</p>

<p>明确了科研的定义，下面我们讨论科研的意义。</p>

<h3 id="section-3">科研的意义</h3>
<hr />

<p>从上面我们可以看到科研的专业性主义倾向，在专业主义倾向下，人们往往越来越多的讨论科研的意义。往往我们的课题申请必然会有这么一个项目——该项目的社会意义、经济价值。这是好事，不能全然否定，某种意义上时刻明确投入和产出比才能保证可持续发展，也才能促进人类社会的进步。特别是对于中国这样的发展中国家，我们提倡科研意义、价值是有道理的。</p>

<p>但是我们从科研的历史中就可以发现科研的根基在于发现未知，广义上，科研甚至就是好奇心驱动的。</p>

<p>简单来说，你怎么去定义未知事物的价值？在茫茫的黑夜中前行的人怎么能知道自己是不是能到达温暖的远方？首先能不能到是个问题，到了之后是不是那么美好是另一个问题。所以我发现很多时候，其实科研意义这一栏写的都和王子和公主的童话差不多。有个特别邪恶的老巫婆(社会急需解决的问题)，现在王子(科学家)沿着确定的康庄大道（科研方法，项目计划)到达城堡(新的发现或新的发明)救出受苦的公主(饱受困扰的人类)战胜老巫婆，从此他们幸福的生活在一起。</p>

<p>但是往往历史不是必然的决定，从混沌的角度看，科学探索这么复杂的体系，其实是很难确定它的发展方向和到达的时间的。无数的偶然决定了我们的现在，未来的发展其实也是无数的偶然汇聚而成的。当然更进一步，就是平行宇宙或者多重时空的观点了。我觉得从这个意义上来说，写科研意义本身就是值得商榷的。</p>

<p>其次科研的意义还和人们的价值判断有关。</p>

<p>很多的时候，有的科研比较冷门，不是因为它本身的价值不高而是受制于各种条件导致人们无法认识到他的价值。比如易辛(Ising)模型,
这个被无数科学家在物理、化学、生物学、社会学中使用的模型，特别适合描述只有短程相互作用存在的情形。但在Ising1920年首次在博士论文中提出时并没有得到重视，直到1960年才受到广泛关注。客观上说，易辛(Ising)模型不受重视是有物理原因的，因为Ising只是解决了一维的模型，而且一维易辛模型没有人们感兴趣的相变性质。而Ising本人对于二维模型更是直接猜了个错误的答案。直到1944年Onsager才解出了二维Ising模型，但是直到杨政宁给出简明的证明人们才理解Onsager的方法。而三维至今无解，只能数值逼近。最根本的原因在于计算机还未发明，Ising的模型特别适合计算机模拟，而1960年代正是计算机蓬勃发展的时候。再比如Higgs获得今年的诺贝尔物理奖，算是得到了科学界正式的承认，但是他能拿奖很大程度归功于欧洲核子中心CERN的卓越工作。尤记得2012年7月暑假暑期学校，我在南京看CERN关于Higgs粒子的发布会，Higgs老爷子在发布会后的感言中第一句感叹就是——“很高兴我能活着看到你们发现它！”</p>

<p>当然有的时候则更多的是某种人为因素了，比如2011年诺贝尔化学奖获得者Shechtman则是在发现准晶后丢掉在美国的教职，因为化学界大牛Pauling直接反对准晶，甚至说出了“There
is no such thing as quasicrystals, only quasi-scientists.” The head of
Shechtman’s research group told him to “go back and read the textbook”
and a couple of days later “asked him to leave for ’bringing disgrace’
on the
team.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>(<code>甚至Shechtman所在研究组的负责人告诉Shechtman回去多读读教科书，不久又对他更是直接下逐客令,认为Shechtman给整个研究组抹黑。</code>)。至于20世纪苏联政府压制的科学研究的现象更多，比如李森科主义对于孟德尔基于基因的遗传理论的压制就是一种典型。这与Pauling相比，没有任何区别，都是强权对于科学研究价值判断的扭曲。可以想见当时在苏联研究基因的科学家的工作会受到什么样的价值判断。</p>

<p>最后也是最重要的一点——科研的本质决定了价值判断的唯一标准只能是时间！</p>

<p>科研的本质是什么？归根到底是创新！什么是创新？一定是针对人们固有观点的一次突破。既然是突破那一定是打破人们旧有认识的。我们怎么用旧有的知识体系去衡量创新的价值？</p>

<p>很多时候，我们会在自然科学史上看到的某个科学家的工作可能5年，10年，乃至20年无人关注，但是有时候一个偶然的突破或者关联人们就发现了这项工作的价值。</p>

<p>比如前段时间报纸上沸沸扬扬报道，中国科学家发明了隐身衣。而隐身衣的关键原理在于负折射率材料。负折射率材料最早是Victor
Veselago在1967年第一次提出的。可惜的是东西方的冷战加上Veselago用俄文写就的论文本省对于外界很陌生，最最重要的是人们不相信这种材料存在。从牛顿开始到麦克斯伟成熟的电磁学的伟大传统怎么可能允许负折射率存在？知道他的论文33后，人们才发现借助纳米技术可以很简单的制造负折射率材料。事实上，人们手工加工材料就可以用合适的结构实现微波波段的负折射率材料，但是很难相信负折射率材料存在的想法万股地挡住了人们实现负折射率材料的价值。四元数也是如此，哈密顿在1843年就发明了四元数，但是直到爱因斯坦的描述四维时空时才得到重视并被直接使用。</p>

<p>所以科研确实需要明确价值意识，但是我们是不是在强调价值意识的同时更多的明确下价值本身是不是值得考虑呢？</p>

<p>最后引用丁肇中先生在接受采访时的一句话“一个做科学家的人,为拿诺贝尔奖来工作，是非常危险的。”我们不应该被专业主义绑架，</p>

<h2 id="section-4">关于物理与哲学关系的思考</h2>
<p>========================</p>

<p>这部分来自老师上课的一句话——“任何学科的最高端都是哲学”。这正好和我曾经的想法吻合，这部分我在自己的个人Blog有专门的一篇博文写这个感受，当时只是朦胧的感觉，现在感觉有了更深的体会。那篇Blog是今年9月30日上“固体材料”课得到的感受，这里我想把这篇名为”关于物理思维的思考<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>“的文章扩展开来，阐述下自己从物理角度对于这个问题的看法。</p>

<p>9月30日上固体材料课程，老师在讲解Ginzburg-Landau(金兹堡—朗道,GL)方程的时候，这么总结物理：</p>

<p><strong>一流的物理=哲学的思维+数学的表达</strong></p>

<p>这里我不讨论数学表达的作用，因为这个问题比较复杂，我集中在哲学思维上。</p>

<p>简单介绍下Ginzburg-Landau(金兹堡—朗道,GL)方程。所谓Ginzburg-Landau方程其实就是描述超导的一个唯象方程，这个方程是BCS理论提出之前对于超导现象最完善的解释。事实上，除了缺少对于超导电子是借助声子耦合的库帕对这一条，Ginzburg-Landau方程基本上解释了超导当时的全部已知实验事实。</p>

<p>但是Ginzburg-Landau(金兹堡—朗道,GL)方程方程建立的基础是如下几个简单的事实：</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>序参量表示超导过程且突变处序参量为零，序参量平方代表超导电流密度；</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>自由能可以写成序参量的幂级数展开；</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>自由能展开式的各项系数和温度T有关；</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>这么简单的理论假设，再加上数学就表达可以得出超导的唯象描述，给出超导的宏观量子现象，超导的磁场穿透深度等等。</p>

<p>在Ginzburg-Landau方程的假设中，尤其以第一个假设最为重要，他是Ginzburg和Landau哲学思想的核心体现。他们认为所谓超导其实就是导体在一定的条件下发生了相变从普通的导体变为超导体。而相变，顾名思义就是从一个状态到另外一个状态，在超导中就是从有电阻的普通态到超导态。这样的相变一定是有一个量发生了突变，可能是这个量的一阶导数也可能是一阶导数连续，二阶导数突变等等。Ginzburg-Landau方程就用序参量T来表示突变，从而准确把握住超导的相变本质，直接给出可以使用的方程。</p>

<p>下面来看看量子力学，以波尔的量子论为例，主要是这么三个假设：</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>原子定态；</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>轨道假说；</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>电子跃迁；</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>而爱因斯坦的狭义相对论更是只有两个假设：</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>各系均权；</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>光速不变；</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>更绝的是玻尔兹曼建立统计力学，只有一个假设：各微观态等概率出现，除此以外，任何的结论都可以用严格逻辑推导出来。统计力学将微观世界和宏观世界联系起来，
爱因斯坦曾经这样评价统计力学“难以置信，这样少的假设就联系起微观和宏观两个不同的世界”。</p>

<p>而物理学本身其实就是从假设开始的，对于古希腊的科学家们而言，他们的一个活动就是对于世界提出自己的假设。比如被罗素称为：“Western
philosophy begins with
Thales”的Thales就喜欢对世界作出假设，他认为世界是水组成的（Water as a
first principle）<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>。其实维基百科的页面中还有这面一段描述：“Thales
attempted to explain natural phenomena without reference to mythology
and was tremendously influential in this respect. Almost all of the
other Pre-Socratic philosophers follow him in attempting to provide an
explanation of ultimate substance, change, and the existence of the
world without reference to mythology. Those philosophers were also
influential, and eventually Thales’ rejection of mythological
explanations became an essential idea for the scientific revolution. He
was also the first to define general principles and set forth
hypotheses, and as a result has been dubbed the “Father of Science”,
though it is argued that Democritus is actually more deserving of this
title.(<code>泰勒斯试图不依赖神话和宗教来解释自然现象，在他之后的哲学家们遵循这个传统，最终泰勒斯对于迷信的拒绝成为现代科学革命的源头。他也是第一个试图借助经验观察和理性思维来解释世界的人，所以他也被称为科学之父，虽然有人也说德漠克里克才是科学之父</code>)”概括而言，虽然有争议，但是Thales不借助神话和宗教，对于世界大胆提出自己的假设可以认为是科学的滥觞。事实上，根据本科母校南京大学物理学院李俊老师在给我们讲解高亮课上的说法，Thales是“一切自然科学之父”。</p>

<p>当然，对于“科学之父”大家可以有不同的看法，我倒是非常支持这个看法，那就是：自然科学的范式千年不变的就是——假设，检验，修正，再假设的循环。所以一流的物理=哲学的思维+数学的表达，更恰当的说法可能是：一流的物理学家运用他们的哲学思维提出天才的有独到创见的物理假设，再加上细致的数学分析得到对于这个世界的描述。</p>

<p>所以往往一个科学的最最精华或者说贡献最大的部分就是包含他独特创见的假设部分，这部分包含了哲学的思想。比如大家都说爱因斯坦，都说他的相对论。但是对于相对论，其实最关键的部分就是：各系均权，光速不变。前者定义了不同参考系中物理定律的规律一致，后者则包含光也是需要传播时间和光速最快这两个概念。所有的志怪神奇都是来自于此。</p>

<p>为什么第一流的物理学家都是哲学家？</p>

<p>因为只有哲学家才能直接抵达本质，用本质思考。我非常同意老师上课时讲的一个观点“哲学是抽离了实证的”，哲学是纯粹的思辩，是最集中的关于本质的思考。它甚至不需要这个世界实际存在，在最高的层次上给出抽象。</p>

<p>很多的时候，我们做的工作复杂难解，只是我们离本质太远以至于我们没办法体会出这些简洁的美丽。从前面的例子里面可以发现，物理或者说科学就是一个提出假设再验证的过程。而最最精华的部分就在假设上，物理学家往往是直接想出了一个精彩的点子，这个点子就直接抵达了问题的本质，也是我们思考的终极目标。这个假设中的闪光点往往和哲学是相同的，异曲同工，甚至可以说往往是一致的。比如康德第一个提出星云说，不论康德是不是真的了解星云说背后需要的数学或者实验观察支持，他的假设就是一个天才的创见。按照维基百科的说法：”<em>In
the General History of Nature and Theory of the Heavens</em> (1755),Immanuel
Kant laid out the Nebular hypothesis, in which he deduced that the Solar
System formed from a large cloud of gas, a nebula. He thus attempted to
explain the order of the solar system, seen previously by Newton as
being imposed from the beginning by
God.<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup>(<code>康德在自己的书《天体的基本特性和理论历史》中提出了星云假说，他认为太阳系从大块星云中形成。以此为基础，他试图解释宇宙的形成和规律，而这在以前被牛顿认为是上帝的创造。</code>)”</p>

<p>当然这里插一句，有了这个伟大的想法还不够，还需要将这个想法用数学表达。物理不是文科。物理是精确的科学，天才的想法要用数学表达，得出的结论用数学的形式展示。如果说法拉第的时代，人们需要的数学还不多，那么现在这个时代没有数学寸步难行。主要的原因在于，数学可以更加准确地揭示规律而不是模糊地定性判断。人们越来越偏爱精确的控制。</p>

<p>不过，这并不否认哲学假设的重要性，恰恰相反，在我经历的物理教育中，我发现大家越来越偏爱数学，偏爱用复杂的数学写出表达式。很多时候，同学讨论的第一句话是“这个公式怎么写？”忽视物理背后哲学思索的后果就是，公式越用越多，数学越写越繁却往往不知道要求解的是什么。最近学习密度泛函理论感受特别深。密度泛函理论在物理和化学上都有广泛的应用，是凝聚态物理和计算化学领域最常用的方法之一。它的中心任务就是求解多体薛定厄方程，但是这个问题在数学上本来就是一个难题，何况还要用量子力学来解。三体牛顿力学的运动问题就被认为不可解的了，何况还要在薛定厄方程的基础上去求解？但是密度泛函理论可以。它的哲学思想其实就是用电子密度表示体系的一切性质和自恰计算。这样就把复杂的多体问题转化为单体的自恰计算来求解。但是很多人其实直接利用已有的程序进行体系性质的计算，全然不顾我们需要的是什么。正如Fritz-Haber研究所的P.
Kratzer教授所指出的那样——“So far, this tool has high credibility. To
maintain this high standard, the users ought to perform each individual
project with utmost care.One has to be aware of the principal
limitations of the DFT approach and of the unavoidable approximations
which enable us to do large-scale calculations for the systems of real
interest.(<code>目前为止，这些计算工具都有足够的可靠性，但是为了保持高质量的计算结果，所有的使用者都该非常小心。任何使用者都需要知道密度泛函理论的局限性并知道那些为了让我们能够计算感兴趣的体系而不得不作出的近似</code>)”可以说忽略了物理，计算的结果就毫无意义了。</p>

<p>所以，一句话总结，无论从历史还是现实：</p>

<p><strong>一流的物理=哲学的思维+数学的表达</strong></p>

<p>哲学的思维往往是更加重要的创新！</p>

<h1 id="section-5">** 总结</h1>

<p>谢谢老师的指导，希望下学期还可以学习老师的课程。</p>

<p>最后，本文在ArchLinux平台用TeXlive2013自带的写成，感谢ddswhu 和 小
L在GPL许可证下分享的
LaTeX模板，他们的模板非常实用而且美观同时我可以自由使用和修改并形成文章。</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <cheap_wholesale_patriots_brandon_spikes_alternate_signed_jersey.html>
</cheap_wholesale_patriots_brandon_spikes_alternate_signed_jersey.html>
      <p><a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dan_Shechtman">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dan_Shechtman</a><a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p><a href="http://iphyer.github.io/blog/2013/09/30/physics/">http://iphyer.github.io/blog/2013/09/30/physics/</a><a href="#fnref:3" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4">
      <p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thales">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thales</a><a href="#fnref:4" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:5">
      <p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Immanuel_Kant">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Immanuel_Kant</a><a href="#fnref:5" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
